To solve this problem, we will do another
conversion to convert the points value on
line 4 to a string. The str function converts
a value to a string, so I will wrap the str
function around points, through placing the cursor
in front of the word, points, typing str, and then
surrounding the word points in parentheses. Let’s
rerun the code. I will enter a whole number, and
the code works perfectly. I will run this code and
enter a float value, 2.2, and as often happens,
solving one problem causes another. Let’s analyze
what is happening here. The input on line 2 is
a string. We are being told that the value 2.2,
which I entered, is invalid for an integer. Think
about it. Integers are whole numbers, right?
We are being told here that this value cannot
be converted to a whole number from a string.
Thus, let’s try converting the original input
to a float, as one would think we can convert
one number type to another. I will wrap the
float function around the input statement on line
2, run the code, and this time, after entering a
float value, everything converts correctly. Let’s
run this code again, using an integer value to
ensure that it still works. It does. Let’s recap
what we have learned about converting data types.
Converting data types is necessary to make data
usable in a situation. Also, we learned that data
captured via inputs are strings of data, so
if we use input data in numeric calculations,
the data needs to be converted to a number.
Finally, Python cannot convert what is not
possible, such as a string, entered as a float to
an integer, at least not through the int function.